<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>BLOG_NAME</title>
 <link href="YOUR_URL/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="YOUR_URL"/>
 <updated>2013-07-14T10:16:44-04:00</updated>
 <id>BLOG_URL</id>
 <author>
   <name>BLOG_NAME</name>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>5 Ways Ear Training Makes You a Better Musician</title>
   <link href="YOUR_URL/5-ways-ear-training-makes-you-a-better-musician.html"/>
   <updated>2013-07-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>BLOG_URL/5-ways-ear-training-makes-you-a-better-musician</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ear training is one of the most valuable things you can practice as a musician. For all of the theory that you can memorize or work out on instrument, at the end of the day you still need to be able to hear it. And the ability to instantly recognize and understand what you're hearing will help you in a number of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. The Ability to 'Hear' Music Theory&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take one of my favorite scales, the melodic minor. I can remember trying to learn it before I took up ear training seriously and it was frustrating. This was because I was learning it from theory and fretboard patterns alone. Don't get me wrong, those are an important part of the process of learning a new scale, but they pale in comparison to being able to hear and understand exactly what makes up a scale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the melodic minor, bring able to instantly recognize the minor 3rd and the major 7th as the crucial ingredients to the melodic minor sound, meant that I was not only able to aurally recognize the scale, but I could relate it to the theory as well. That combination makes it incredibly easy to stick in your head.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Significantly Easier to Memorize Tunes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember I've been interested in learning other languages. One of the things you notice when you study languages is that's very easy to learn a word in a new language if you already know it in another. For instance, take the word dog. When I was learning some Spanish I already knew that in Italian it's 'cane' and in French it's 'chien' - so it was very easy to learn it as 'perro' in Spanish. But why is that? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way that memory works is that the more pathways that your brain has to access a memory, the easier it is. For instance if I'm thinking of a particular time when I was on vacation in Sicily then I can remember one of my favorite nights by the incredible sunset from my hotel balcony AND the surprisingly good taste of the 5 Euro jug of wine AND the hilarious moment when my friend chipped his tooth on that jug of wine trying to drink out of it - then I have 3 ways that my brain can access that memory. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for music and memorizing tunes, if I can think of the melody in terms of the sound AND (because of ear training) the exact interval sequence AND how the song makes me feel then I'm much better off than just knowing the sound. NOTE: this is also why it's such a great reason to learn the lyrics of a tune if there are any.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Being Able to Play What You Hear&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's something that's coveted by all musicians - the ability to play what you hear in your head. By training your ears you have an incredible advantage over other musicians as as soon as you hear a melody in your head you already know the notes that you have to play to make it a reality on your instrument. One of my favorite videos on Youtube is George Benson sitting down with Jody Fisher and just seeing the total command that George Benson has over music because he can play exactly what he hears: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/f6pLl3R_tz4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again it comes down to learning it all together - the theory, the technique and the ears at the same time. But being able to instantly understand the intervals and notes you need to play to make use of a scale or a melody in your head makes it much, much easier to improvise. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. Transcribing and Composing Music in No Time&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one may be obvious, but for those who are transcribing and analyzing music, your life becomes incredibly easy when you're immediately recognizing intervals and chord changes. Certainly for jazz, it's a rite of passage to transcribe the music of the greats (and incredibly worthwhile to your understanding of the music and your musicianship in general) and there's no substitute to being able to pick out chord changes and melodies quickly. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same increase in efficiency applies for composing. By being able to understand exactly what you want to sound like, you can quickly note the chord progressions that you're thinking of and how the melody applies to them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5. Enjoying Music More!&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the more I understand about the music I'm listening to, the easier it is for me to enjoy it. I remember the first time I heard jazz and I had no idea what was going on or why anyone would want to listen to it. As I learned more theory and analyzed some tunes I could start to understand what the musicians were actually doing and I started to appreciate the music and the craft behind it much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
By being able to 'hear' what's going on, whether it's classical, jazz or rock, I find it easier to be absorbed by the music and to get the most out of it. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Get Those Ears Working&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music is just sound. That sound can be complicated given time signatures, instrumentation, dynamics, tone, etc.  - but if you can marry the theory that you study with exactly what your ears pick up, there isn't an aspect of your musicianship that you won't improve.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>3 Example Practice Routines to Make You a Better Guitarist</title>
   <link href="YOUR_URL/3-example-practice-routines-to-make-you-a-better-guitarist.html"/>
   <updated>2013-07-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>BLOG_URL/3-example-practice-routines-to-make-you-a-better-guitarist</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As someone who is constantly searching to make better use my practice time, I've gone through the frustration of not having a practice routine that generated results. Initially I was just picking up any of the number of music theory or guitar technique books I've bought over the years and started working on the first thing I thought was interesting.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other times I've struggled with no routine at all and just played songs that I felt like or went through a bunch of licks that I've played a million times. If there's one things I've learned - &lt;b&gt;YOU CAN'T GET BETTER WITHOUT A ROUTINE!&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm hoping that you don't have to go through the same amount of wasted practice time that I did and so I've put together 3 example practice routines that I've used when I've wanted to work on specific skills or add specific licks to my repetoire.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Practice Routine #1: Shaking Off The Rust&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We've all put down our instruments for periods at a time. Whether it's injury, lack of time or no motivation, it happens. The important thing is that you get back to playing your instrument. This is the routine I use when I'm trying to get back on the saddle and I want to make sure a) I don't injure myself b) I get the basics back quickly and c) I stoke my interest in making music.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Warmup: Scales over Chords&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 10 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make sure that my fingers are moving slowing and purposefully while at the same time making sure I'm warming up my ears as well. To do this I will play a track of a the root note repeating of the key I want to work on (e.g. C being played over and over while I'm playing through scales in C or C minor.) I ALWAYS practice this slowly as I'm trying to work on my timing, fingering and ears at the same time. I'll play the scale up and down the guitar neck a couple of times for each scale and then I'll change scales.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this is to get the fingering of the main scales you use back into your fingers getting the sound of them back in your head. Using the backing track functions as a metronome so that you also work on your timing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Triads: Quick Refresher&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 5 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triads are the building blocks of chords and arpeggios and giving them a bit of practice time always pays off. For me I like to put on a click track (again, slowly - maybe 24bpm) and work through some triads to get the shape and sound of chords back in my fingers and ears. A good example of this is starting with some root triads (root in the bass), play major triads vertically up the neck without worrying about keys. So starting with the root on the 6th string on the 5th fret play a Amaj triad, Dmaj triad, Gmaj triad and Cmaj triad. Then move up to the 12th fret and play them descending (Gmaj, Dmaj, Amaj, Emaj.) &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work through major, minor, diminshed and augmented focusing on the fingering and the sound of each.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Picking &amp;amp; Chromatic Scales&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 5 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't forget about your right hand! We're going slow because I'm paranoid about getting a repetive stress injury doing something I love so I like to put in a bit of time on my right hand technique as well. Focusing on alternate picking with my right hand and fretting with my left hand with as little tension as possible I play up and down the strings horizontally from the 1st to the 12th fret and back.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Playing Songs&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 20 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I'm using this practice routine I've been bored, busy or injured so I want to make sure I'm playing the music that got me into guitar in the first place. Now that I've warmed up my ears and my fingers I like to play through the music that makes me happy. For me I'll go through some jam tracks on Youtube to get some improvising in and then I'll play through some folk/rock songs. Depending on the mood it could be anything but what's important is that I'm playing through my repetoire and enjoying what I'm doing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Practice Routine #2: Performance Ready&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I know I'll be playing in front of people I want to make sure I know the songs inside and out. For each song I have a particular routine that I use to break down the song to understand it and internalize it as much as possible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Warmup: Listening&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 30 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a version or some versions of the song that you like, put together a playlist and throw it on repeat. Listen to it over and over, each time focusing on certain aspects of it. I like to separately pay particular attention to the timing (needs to get those changes down!) the phrasing of the melody, the structure of the solos (if there are any) and without a doubt, I want to memorize the lyrics the song has any. I can't begin to stress the importance of that. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The better you know the song inside and out, the easier it will be to analyze, memorize and riff off of. What are you favorite parts? Things you would change? Things you might want to do differently?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Learn Those Changes&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 15 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have the structure of the music in your head, it's time to learn the changes and get yourself playing through the song. Start basic and don't worry about the extensions to start. (I'm usually focused on jazz tunes but I work through this same routine for all styles.) Play it straight and get the feel of the changes in your ears and under your fingers.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you can play it through straight, start to play with it. Any areas where you can play with timing? Play with how you're fingering the chords, add some extensions, etc. - the more comfortable you are with the structure of the tune the better prepared you'll be to make it your own.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Improvise and Extend&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 15 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you're trying to nail a note for note imitation of another musician, you need to find ways to make a song your own. Whether that's transposing it to your vocal register, altering the chords and fingerings to make it easier to play or suit your style better, or just getting it to the point where you can play it comfortably, you have to experiment. Play over the recordings you like and improvise, vamp and jam. Listen for phrases and notes that you like and want to incorporate into your version.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I like to do is break down the piece into 1, 2 or 4 bar phrases. I'll record myself playing changes and I'll loop it. Then I'll either work on just the chords, just the melody, or just some improv over that small section. Work on the song bit by bit, section by section and focus on the parts that give you trouble.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Practice Routine #3: Maintenance &amp; Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I love to play guitar. I also like to feel like I'm improving all the time. In general I like to have a routine in place for practicing just about every time I pick up the guitar. Here's what I use when I'm working on a specific skill.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Warmup: Scales Over Chords&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 10 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to how I've listed it before, I like to play scales with a metronome or preferably a backing track in the background to get my fingers and ears warmed up. It's always good too to pick a key you haven't used in a while and say the notes to yourself while you play it. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/z_HsFp-OuGo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Play the scale vertically and horizontally. Mix in arpeggios and some licks that you know. But get your timing down and work on hearing how it sounds against the chords.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ear Training&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 15 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eartracker.com&quot;&gt;Ear Tracker&lt;/a&gt; to make this part of my practice sessions way more efficient. I really do believe it's the key to getting better fast. I like to work on intervals and chord progressions where I'm having difficulties and track my progress from practice session to practice session.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving my ears means that when I pick the specific technique or theory that I'm working on, I know that I'll be able to 'hear' the theory or style much better and immediately recognize the intervals that give it its particular sound. Whether it's working on the minor scales in gypsy jazz or hearing the style of a new song I'm transcribing, this is how I make sure I'm ready.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Technique Breakdown&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 15 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll break out the metronome and work on the technique at this point. I do this with licks, scales, chord progressions, chord voicings, etc. - whatever it is that I really want to learn at the time. At this point my fingers are warmed, up my ears are warmed up and I can get started on working the focus of my study.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This usually involves me going through the fingerings and thinking about what I'm trying to accomplish - the important part here is to make sure that I understand what I'm trying to get better at and how I want to add it to my repetoire.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Technique Application&lt;/b&gt; - Time: 15 Minutes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I've got a better understanding of the theory behind the technique, I immediately set about putting it to use. Fire up some loops of chord progressions (I like to use either pedals or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.irealb.com/&quot;&gt;iRealB&lt;/a&gt;) and I will work through applying the technique or licks in a practical situation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I'm trying to do here is to make sure that I'm putting this new skill to use immediately in a musical context. Theory is fairly useless to a musician if it's just sitting in your head. You need to be able to call upon it and make use of it on the instrument (or with composition) in order to incorporate it in your skillset.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;I Hope This Helps!&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, or suggestions on other practice routines you like, feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:brad@bradmilne.ca&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; directly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>